Guide to the Hervey Allen Papers, 1831-1965 SC.1952.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Family Papers, 1831-1965; IX.
  - Genealogy, Financial, and Official Documents, 1831-1930; 4.
    Included in this subseries are genealogical and official documents of Hervey Allen's families. In this subseries is the oldest document in the papers, a marriage certificate between John Gill and Anna Caldwell dated at February 24, 1831. Also included are the Golden Wedding invitations and mementos of both Hervey Allen's great-grandparents, Edward Allen Sr. and Amelia Bindley Allen in 1866, and his grandparents, Colonel Edward Jay Allen and Elizabeth Robinson Allen in 1907. Other documents include estate and financial documents.
    - Certificate of Marriage of John Gill and Anna Caldwell, 1831 (Box 173, Folder 1)
    - Estate of Helen M. Allen Documents, 1890-1922 (Box 173, Folder 2)
    - Estate of Helen M. Allen Trustee Documents, 1926-1930 (Box 173, Folder 3)
    - Genealogy (Box 173, Folder 4)
      Contains "Notes for Family History" which traces Allen history from England to Pittsburgh. Also contains detailed biography of Edward Jay Allen, a handwritten family tree, and history of "Edgehill."
    - General Financial Documents, 1897-1925 (Box 173, Folder 5-6)
    - Golden Wedding: Edward Allen and Millicent (Amelia Bindley) Allen (great-grandparents), 1866 (Box 173, Folder 7)
    - Golden Wedding: Edward Jay Allen and Elizabeth Robinson Allen and General Messages (grandparents), 1907; 1899-1915 (Box 173, Folder 8)
    - Insurance, 1896-1918 (Box 173, Folder 9)
    - Tax Forms, 1891-1918 (Box 173, Folder 10)
    - Wills, Testaments, and Memoirs (Box 173, Folder 11)
  - Creative Works, 1855-1965; 5.
    Various members of the Allen family were also writers, including his grandfather who wrote the Civil War inspired poem, "The Veteran." His father, William Hervey Allen Sr., wrote amateur poetry as well. Colonel Edward Jay Allen's works can all be found in his own subseries, Boxes 156-160. In this subseries are numerous creative endeavors written by other members of the Allen family including his wife Ann Andrews Allen, and his great-uncle, William Hervey Allen.
    - Ann Allen
      - Certain Letters of Hervey Allen with Notes by Ann Andrews Allen '28, in Vassar Alumnae Magazine, December 1965 (Box 173, Folder 12)
      - Sarah Simon: Character Atlantean, in The Bermudian, March 1956 (Box 173, Folder 13)
    - William Hervey Allen (father)
      - Australia (Box 173, Folder 14)
      - [To Miss Anna Garrison Bennett], 1887 (Box 173, Folder 15)
    - William Hervey Allen (uncle)
      - The Last Trip, in The Knickerbocker, December 1855 (Box 173, Folder 16)
  - Photographs, 1857-1949; 6.
    This subseries contains the bulk of all photographs in the papers. When possible, folders are listed by identified individuals and date. If there is no discernable name and/or date associated, photographs were grouped as unidentified individuals, groups, or places. Other materials found here are photographic negatives, photographic reproductions, and associated materials found with photographs. Please note: folders are fastened with plastic clips, please use precaution upon perusal. Place folders flat on a stable surface upon removal of clips.
    Oversized photographs of Hervey Allen and the Allen family exist in Boxes 189-194.
    - Individuals
      - Amelia Bindley (Mrs. Edward Allen, great grandmother) (Box 174, Folder 1)
      - Ann Allen (wife) (Box 174, Folder 2)
      - Annette Allen (niece), 1921 (Box 174, Folder 3)
      - Bishop Carleton Hunt (brother-in-law) (Box 174, Folder 4)
      - Doris Appel (secretary) (Box 174, Folder 5)
      - Edna Allen Rickmers (aunt) (Box 174, Folder 6)
      - Edward Allen (paternal great grandfather) (Box 174, Folder 7)
      - Edward Jay Allen (paternal grandfather) (Box 174, Folder 8)
      - Edward Allen (uncle) (Box 174, Folder 9)
      - Edward Jay Allen III (brother), 1911-1913 (Box 174, Folder 10)
      - Elizabeth Allen (sister) (Box 174, Folder 11)
      - Elizabeth R. Allen (paternal grandmother) (Box 174, Folder 12)
      - Friends: DuBose Heyward (Box 174, Folder 13)
      - Friends: General (File-cabinet 14)
      - Friends: Robert Frost, 1947 (File-cabinet 14, Folder 15)
      - Gill Family, 1865 (File-cabinet 14, Folder 16)
      - Helen Allen (sister-in-law) (File-cabinet 14, Folder 17)
      - Helen Eby Myers Allen (mother), 1865-1918 (Box 175, Folder 1-3)
      - Helen Mar Allen (sister) (Box 175, Folder 4)
      - Helen Mar Myers Gill (maternal grandmother), 1857-1900 (Box 175, Folder 5)
      - Hervey Allen (baby portraits), 1889-1895 (Box 175, Folder 6)
      - Hervey Allen (childhood photos), 1896-1905 (Box 175, Folder 7-8)
      - Hervey Allen, 1909-1918 (Box 175, Folder 9)
        Photographs of Hervey Allen at the Naval Academy.
      - Hervey Allen, 1920-1930 (Box 176, Folder 1)
      - Hervey Allen, 1931-1939 (Box 176, Folder 2)
      - Hervey Allen, 1940-1949 (Box 176, Folder 3)
      - Hervey Allen Portraits: Headshots, ca. 1930s (Box 176, Folder 4)
      - Hervey Allen Portraits: Artwork (in likeness of), 1925-1942 (Box 176, Folder 5)
      - Hervey Allen Publicity (Box 176, Folder 6)
      - Hervey and Ann Allen (Box 176, Folder 7)
      - Jacob Myers, Mr. and Mrs. (maternal great grandparents) (Box 176, Folder 8)
      - John Gill (maternal great grandfather) (Box 176, Folder 9)
      - John Gill, Mrs. (maternal great grandmother) (Box 176, Folder 10)
      - Mable Allen (Mrs. Harold Allen) (Box 176, Folder 11)
      - Mary Ann Allen (daughter) (Box 176, Folder 12)
      - May L. Allen (aunt), 1901-1905 (Box 176, Folder 13)
      - Rebecca Turner (great aunt) (Box 176, Folder 14)
      - Richard Francis Allen (son) (Box 176, Folder 15)
      - Sylvia Allen (niece) (Box 176, Folder 16)
      - Unidentified Individuals (Box 177, Folder 1-2)
      - Uriah Myers (maternal grandfather) (Box 177, Folder 3)
      - William H. Allen (father), 1860-1911 (Box 177, Folder 4)
      - William H. Allen (great uncle) (Box 177, Folder 5)
      - Winthrop Allen (brother) (Box 177, Folder 6)
    - Groups
      - Allen Children (Box 177, Folder 7)
      - Allen Family, 1897-1905 (Box 177, Folder 8)
      - Allen Family, 1949 (Box 177, Folder 9)
      - Friends (Box 177, Folder 10)
      - Unidentified (Box 177, Folder 11)
    - Places and Other Material
      - Charleston, South Carolina, 1924-1938 (Box 178, Folder 1)
      - Edgehill Home, 1899-1900 (Box 178, Folder 2)
        These are photographs of the home Colonel Edward Jay Allen kept on Braddock Road, Pittsburgh. According to inscriptions on the back of these photographs, the home was built at about 1879. The Allens lived here until 1900 when it was purchased by a M. Lovejoy who demolished the home soon after.
      - Estates and Residences (Box 178, Folder 3)
      - Johnny Appleseed's Grave (Box 178, Folder 4)
      - Landscapes and General Travel (Box 178, Folder 5)
      - Mexican Border, Ysleta, 1916-1917 (Box 178, Folder 6)
      - Negatives (Box 178, Folder 7)
      - Other Material Found with Photographs (Box 178, Folder 8)
      - Reproductions and Photographs of Figurines (Box 178, Folder 9)
  - Journals and Scrapbooks, 1837-1934; 7.
    This subseries includes personal journals and scrapbooks composed by various members of the Allen family including George T. Allen, great-uncle of Hervey Allen. At the age of 20, George was killed on May 6, 1847 on board The New Hampshire, a steamboat captained by his older brother, William Hervey Allen. First account portrayal of the accident is evident in William's journals. William Hervey, who was deeply affected by the accident, took a great deal of responsibility and sorrow because of it. Mention of the accident is also evident in Lloyd's Steamboat Directory and Disasters of the Western Waters, 1856 (in the Hervey Allen personal library collection). Also included here is the Colonel Edward Jay Allen and Elizabeth R. Allen's Golden Wedding Scrapbook.
    - Edward S. White
      - Notebook, 1934 (Box 179, Folder 1)
    - Elizabeth R. Allen (paternal grandmother)
      - Photo Album Containing Portraits of Allen Family, (1857-1882) (Box 179, Folder 2)
      - Scrapbook, Wedding of Edward Jay Allen and Elizabeth Allen, 1866 (Box 179, Folder 3)
    - George T. Allen (great uncle)
      - Diary Containing Accounts of Daily Life in Pittsburgh and on the Steamboat New Hampshire, 1845 (Box 180, Folder 1)
      - Diary Containing Accounts of Daily Life in Pittsburgh and on the Steamboat New Hampshire, 1846 (Box 180, Folder 2)
      - Scrapbook of Newspaper Clippings Concerning the Steamboat New Hampshire, 1847 (Box 180, Folder 3)
    - Helen Myers (maternal grandmother)
      - Diary, 1851 (Box 180, Folder 4)
      - Diary, 1879 (Box 180, Folder 5)
    - Hervey Allen
      - Scrapbook of Miscellaneous Newspaper Clippings Collected by Hervey, 1922-1930 (Box 180, Folder 6)
      - Diary, 1924 (Box 180, Folder 7)
      - The Gossip: According to John, Scrapbook Containing Letters from and Photographs of John Young, 1925-1927 (Box 181, Folder 1)
    - William Hervey Allen (father)
      - Brown Scrapbook, 1857-1880 (Box 181, Folder 2)
      - Diary, 1877-1879 (Box 181, Folder 3)
      - Yearbook, 1921 (Box 181, Folder 4)
      - Date Book, 1922 (Box 181, Folder 5)
      - Date Book, 1923 (Box 181, Folder 6)
    - William Hervey Allen (great uncle)
      - Book of Fift, Notebook of Mathematical Reference Collected by Allen, 1837-1897 (Box 182, Folder 1)
      - "Notices of Books," Notebook Containing Summaries and Personal Reviews of Books and Journal Entries Accounting Daily Life and Travels, 1840-1841 (Box 182, Folder 2)
      - Personal Diary Accounting Daily Life on the steamboat New Hampshire, 1842 (Box 182, Folder 3)
      - Scrapbook of Newspaper Clippings of Poems and Handwritten Quotations, 1844 (Box 182, Folder 4)
      - Scrapbook of Newspaper Clippings concerning the steamboat New Hampshire, current events, local happenings, and Hungarian President Kossuth, 1847-1853 (Box 182, Folder 5)
      - The New Hampshire Steamer Album of Poems, Illustrations, and Newspaper Clippings Regarding the Death of George and also William, ten years later, 1845-1857 (Box 183, Folder 1)
      - Diary Accounting Work on the Steamboat New Hampshire and Daily Life in Pittsburgh, 1845 (Box 183, Folder 2)
      - Review of Books Perused By..., Notebook Containing Personal Reviews and Summaries of Books, 1847-1851 (Box 183, Folder 3)
      - Book of Recorded Quotations and Poems, 1847 (Box 183, Folder 4)
      - Scrapbook of Newspaper Clippings of Poems and Recorded Poems, 1849-1963 (Box 183, Folder 5)
      - Diary as Clerk on the Steamboat Hiram Powers, 1849 (Box 183, Folder 6)
      - Bible, 1850-1852 (Box 184, Folder 1)
      - Bible Given to Edward Jay Allen, 1851 (Box 184, Folder 2)
      - Diary Accounting Work on The Steamboat Norma and Daily Life in Pittsburgh, 1851 (Box 184, Folder 3)
      - Diary Accounting Work on The Steamboat Norma and Daily Life in Pittsburgh, 1854 (Box 184, Folder 4)
  - Ephemera, 1865-1949; 8.
    Mementos, personal items, postcards, and newspaper clippings gathered by the Allen family including a sermon pamphlet from the Presbyterian Church given just days after the assassination of President Lincoln.
    - A Gift for My Mother, Helen's Handiwork in Harrisburg, 1873 (Box 185, Folder 1)
    - A Letter in the Collection of Benjamin Franklin (reproduction) (Box 185, Folder 2)
    - Calvary Church of Pittsburgh, 1924 (Box 185, Folder 3)
    - General Family Papers (Box 185, Folder 4)
    - Hervey Allen Personal Items (Box 185, Folder 5-6)
    - Jefferson Davies for President (Box 185, Folder 7)
    - Newspaper Clippings, Assassination of President Lincoln and President McKinley, 1865-1901 (Box 185, Folder 8)
    - The Philadelphia Directory (reproduction), [1791] (Box 185, Folder 9)
    - Postcards (Box 185, Folder 10-16)
    - Presbyterian Church of Harrisburg Program, 1865 (Box 185, Folder 17)
      Sermon about Lincoln's assassination.
    - Shadyside Literary Society Entertainment, 1876 (Box 185, Folder 18)
    - Souvenir from the Musee Historique Candadien - a Wax Museum (Box 185, Folder 19)
    - Weekly Memo, 1949 (Box 185, Folder 20)
- Oversized Material, 1856-1953; X.
  This series is dedicated to housing oversized or three-dimensional materials including artwork, galleys, newspapers, and familial ephemera. Some materials in this series are on permanent display, please see Special Collections staff for more information.
  - Artwork Collection, ca. 1880-1933; 1.
    Featured here are various art works including pieces by John White Alexander, who lived with the Allen family as a young man. While working as a telegraph boy, the orphaned Alexander was taken under Edward Jay Allen's tutelage. Allen provided financial support and encouragement to the young Alexander, allowing him an artist studio in his home at "Edgehill." A photograph of Alexander as a young man and the rest of the Allen family posing outside of "Edgehill" exists in the Family Oversized, Box 193.
    Other art works include prints, reproductions, and oversized Anthony Adverse posters. Some of these materials are on permanent display, please see Special Collections staff for access to these materials.
    - Artwork on Display
      - [Anthony Adverse Film Poster] (Box 185, Frame 1)
      - [Portrait of Edward Allen (great-grandfather)] (Box 185, Frame 2)
      - [Portrait of Mrs. Edward Allen, Millicent (Amelia Bindley) Allen (great-grandmother)] (Box 185, Frame 3)
    - John Alexander
      - [Edward Jay Allen, Three-Quarter-Length Portrait, Standing, Face Right], 1899 (Box 185, Frame 4)
      - [Lobster Painted on Wood, Xmas], 1880 (Box 186, Folder 1)
      - [Proof of Drawing of Robert L. Stevenson at Bournemouth, Presented to Hervey Allen by Mrs. John Alexander], 1886 (Box 186, Folder 2)
      - Clippings and Correspondence To John Alexander, 1915-1933 (Box 186, Folder 3)
    - John Bennett
      - House of The Doctor of the Dead, Charleston, S.C. (Box 186, Folder 4)
    - Prints and Other Art, 1921
      - [Christ Icon] (Box 186, Folder 5)
      - Downtown, The El / Lower Manhattan by John Marin, 1921 (Box 186, Folder 6)
        Separated Material
        Item is on shelf next to Box 186.
      - [Reproduction of Portrait of Woman Standing] by John Alexander (Box 186, Folder 7)
      - [Reproduction of Woman with a Ring] by John Alexander (Box 186, Folder 8)
      - Diorama - Possibly of Anthony Adverse (Map-case 1)
        On top of Map-Case 1.
  - Galleys, 1921-1950; 2.
    This subseries includes galley proofs of Allen's works. Each proof is described on an item-level by title.
    - Box 1 (Box 187)
      - Action at Aquila: Complete Proofs (enclosed), 1938
      - Action at Aquila: Proofs (2 copies), 1938
      - Action at Aquila: Frontmatter and Backmatter (2 copies)
      - Anthony Adverse: Odd-sized proofs, including Book 5 title page and pages 411, 430, 1173, 397, and 469
      - Anthony Adverse: Vol. 1-3 (2 versions of Book 9), 1932
      - Bedford Village: Proofs (3 copies), 1944
      - Carolina Chansons: Complete Proofs, 1922
      - Carolina Chansons: Loose Pages (folder), 1950
      - City in the Dawn: Complete Proofs, 1950
      - City in the Dawn: Sample Printed Sheets (folder), 1950
    - Box 2 (Box 188)
      - The Disinherited: Vol. 1, Albine's Saga (3 copies), 1943
      - The Forest and the Fort: The Disinherited, Vol. 1
      - Green Pastures [By: Marc Connelly]: Complete Proofs
      - [Poetry]
      - New Legends: Complete Proofs, 1929
      - Toward the Morning: Complete Proofs, 1948
      - Toward the Morning: 3-157, Frontmatter, 1948
      - Wampum and Old Gold: Complete Proofs (folder), 1921
      - Wampum and Old Gold: Second Proofs (folder), 1921
  - Hervey Allen General Material, 1906-1948; 3.
    This subseries features oversized materials such as awards and diplomas, blueprints, photographs, literary works and promotional materials regarding Hervey Allen. Hervey Allen's military coat and a honorary flag are featured in box 190 and 195.
    - Awards and Diplomas, 1906-1948 (Box 189)
    - Military Ephemera (Box 190)
    - Works - Manuscripts and Publications, 1919-1949 (Box 191)
    - Works - Promotional Posters; Blueprints to his Homes, 1933-1948 (Box 192)
    - Military Uniform (Box 195)
    - Nautical Charts (Box 195, Tube 1)
      Included are two nautical charts that Hervey Allen used to course his journey on the Chesapeake Bay between Piney Creek, Maryland and his home at Bonfield Manor in Maryland.
  - Family, 1856-1948; 4.
    In this subseries are oversized materials belonging to the Allen family including personal items, ledgers, photographs, obtituaries, and manuscripts. Some highlights include a handwritten poem by Colonel Edward Jay Allen and an oversized photograph of the Allen family pictured with a young John White Alexander at "Edgehill" dated in 1876 (note: photograph is in two pieces).
    - Portrait of Allen Family with John W. Alexander at Edgehill, 1876 (Box 193, Item 1)
    - Unidentified photographs, tents among mountain range and a portrait of young girl, undated (Box 193, Item 2)
    - Poem copied by Hervey Allen in handwriting of grandfather, Edward Jay Allen, undated (Box 193, Item 3)
    - Ledger, notes and bills payable, 1876 (Box 193, Item 4)
    - Book, Mop and the Frisk, accompanied by note that reads, "William and Win's Favorite", undated (Box 193, Item 5)
    - Harmonica (Box 193, Item 6)
    - Gavel (Box 193, Item 7)
    - Straight Razor in leather pouch (Box 193, Item 8)
    - Ledger, Hervey Allen, 1938-1939 (Box 193, Item 9)
    - Leather baby bootie (Box 193, Item 10)
    - Compass in wood enclosure (Box 193, Item 11)
    - Diploma, Universitatis Occidentalis, presented to Edward Jay Allen (Box 193, Item 12)
    - Newpapers containing William Allen's obituary, 1857 (Box 193, Item 13)
    - New Hampshire Steamer Broadside (Box 193, Item 14)
    - Winthop Allen's Portraits of New Mexico, 1948 (Box 193, Item 15)
    - Various Hervey Allen family portraits incuding wife and children (Box 193, Item 16)
    - Broadside and other materials about anniversary of Edward Jay Allen's Civil War service, 1890 and 1904 (Box 193, Item 17)
  - Newspapers, 1874-1953; 5.
    Oversized newspapers relating to Hervey Allen or his family members.
    - Pittsburgh Newspapers with articles on WWI, 1918-1919 (Box 194, Folder 1)
    - Pittsburgh Gazette containing Edward Allen's obituary, 1874 (Box 194, Folder 2)
    - "Writers and Books" sections from Columbia, SC newspaper, The State, 1922-1925 (Box 194, Folder 3)
    - The Saturday Review of Literature, 1922-1925 (Box 194, Folder 4)
    - Various sections from The New York Times, 1922-1925 (Box 194, Folder 5)
    - The Miami Herald, 1949, 1953 (Box 194, Folder 6)